in the final and there will be representatives from the USA, Germany, Ukraine, Canada, Great Britain, Spain, Australia and Malaysia and of course two from Chinese as well in the competition tonight.
It's going to be a thrilling one.
Certainly if the previous two rounds are anything to go by and the home crowd are delighted after the introduction of Javier Garcia.
See, rather unexpectedly, Chris Mears has made it through to a final.
Preliminaries was the best that he could manage at the World Championships in Shanghai last year.
This time round, he's gone too better and made it into the top 12.
This man is very used to being in the top 12.
Twice silver medalist at the Olympics in this very event, Alexandre Departee of Canada.
Ilya Kavasha of Ukraine will certainly be in the mix, as will this man.
All the remaining divers being introduced will be competing for probably a bronze, maybe a silver.
We have maybe a fly in the ointment for the Chinese coming up in just a moment.
We'll introduce him after Troy Dumay has been introduced to the crowd.
There's a few divers who have been diving exceptionally well and consistently well, too.
And here's one of them.
Yann Castillo Puerta.
Second ranked of the Chinese after the semifinals is Chin Kai.
He just missed out on a medal at the World Championships last year in fourth place.
But here's the almost unknown quantity, though we do know what he can do.
Silver medalist at the World Championships last year separating out the Chinese.
Ilya Zakharov.
But the red hot favorite surely is the world champion and Olympic champion He Chong.
ready to do battle once again with 11 other divers.
It could be a very interesting hour and a half or so.
Very unpredictable the first two rounds have been.
No reason to suspect that tonight may not be in a similar vein.
Alongside me, the 2004 Syncro 10 meter silver medalist, Leon Taylor.
Well, we haven't been disappointed so far.
And I think the stakes are going to be notched up just a bit or two tonight.
Well, this is what all the divers have been aiming to do.
You've got to make it through the preliminaries.
You've got to make it through the semi-finals.
And this is where the work starts.
None of the points carry through.
Each of the divers will be performing six dives.
the most difficult dives humanly possible they'll be going in different directions there are five groups of dive there's the forward the backward there's also the inward which is where you stand backwards on your tiptoes but you jump away from the diving board and spin forward there's the reverse which is where you walk down the diving board jumping away from it but spin backwards towards it there's also the twist where you move twist the longitudinally
as well as fitting in somersaults.
And then you get one dive that you can choose any one of those five groups.
So what you're going to see today is, well, if the prelims and semifinals or anything to go by, it's going to be extraordinary.
As indeed with those headphones on that little baby there, almost as big as the young kid's head.
On to the judges.
These are the ones who will have the destiny and the outcome of the men's three meter springboard in their hands.
Would you like me to explain the judging before we kick off, Bob?
Explaining the judges and explaining the judges might be two different things.
I can't explain the judges but I will explain how the judging works in all individual contests.
So there are seven execution judges who mark the diver out of ten.
The two highest and two lowest marks are then crossed off and you will see those appear on your screen with lines through them to leave three raw scores.
Those are then totalled multiplied by the associated degree of difficulty to give the total for that given dive.
All six totals are added together to give the overall placings.
Right now we've marked your card on how it works and what's likely to happen in the next hour and a half.
Let's get on with the action and start with the first round.
First round of six, remember?
Five in the women's competition, six in the men's.
And just sneaking in in the very final qualifying place, number 12.
is Ken Yeo of Malaysia.
29 year old first Olympics for 12 years.
He will quit after these games only made the preliminaries in Sydney in 2000.
His opening dive forward three and a half somersaults with Pike.
Oh, if that's a sign of what is to come, we are in for a real treat.
Kenny O, starting with his forward three and a half, perfectly on the end of the diving board, squeezing into that pike shape, slipping into the water without very much splash.
That's a big opening round dive for him.
Eight eight point fives incoming and a big total score to start off his campaign in this Olympic final.
Yeah, very good opening for him.
Seventy nine point zero five for Kenny O.
A 29 year old from Malaysia.
Now on to Ethan Warren from Australia.
Only one Australian actually entered in this event but he's made it through to the final.
And he will go with a back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
This time not 3.1 but 3.0 degree of difficulty which of course will be what the marks he gets will be multiplied by.
Oh, it's pretty good.
It's straight up and down.
He is, well, that dive was throwing up a little bit too much splash for more than an eight, which is a shame.
The aerial work is good.
Backwards, there's the pike shape, comes out in plenty of time, enters the water.
It's good.
He'll get eights, I'm sure, but it needs to be clean him into the water.
Check out this super slow-mo shot here as he exits the dive, putting his chin back to look at the water, reaches back.
It's pretty good.
Just too much splash.
Yeah, happy enough it would seem with that.
Maybe he's putting a brave face on it, but seventy-two is the opening score for Ethan Warren.
Twenty-year-old from Australia goes into second place for the time being.
Javier Garcia of Spain, training in Canada these days.
Seventh in Rome, 2009 and ninth in Shanghai a year ago.
Is his back two and a half semisault.
He's really coming into form these past few years.
Decided to train overseas and he's certainly been working hard.
He's in great shape.
He used to be a little heavier than that but he's obviously working with a fantastic team in Canada.
Teammate of Alexandre Departee who will be up soon.
That could squeeze eights from the judges.
He's cleaning him into the water than Ethan before him.
Again 3.0 DD.
A couple of eights and a 7.5 to give him a total when you
And they're all up and multiplied of 70.50.
This man's having a great couple of days.
The boy became a man right before the eyes of the Aquatic Centre in London.
Britain's Chris Mears with his opening dive.
One of the easier ones he'll do.
It's all relative, of course.
3.0 degree of difficulty.
Starting dive for Mears back two and a half semisault.
Roy looks pretty steady again and the crowd are enjoying that ripping the roof off.
There's his mum and dad and the rest of his family holding up the tens.
That's only going to get eights.
But there we go.
Smiling before he sets off.
You've got to use this crowd.
You can't block it out.
You've got to smile.
Rise to the occasion.
Exactly what he did in the semi-finals.
And that's a lovely start.
It'll get over 70 points.
Good enough.
Yeah, it's alright.
Not bad at all.
Seventy-two is what we anticipate.
Seventy-two is what we get with three eights multiplied of course by the degree of difficulty giving you seventy-two and that slots him nicely into equal second at the moment.
Alexander Departee.
Again, it's a three point zero.
It's the back two and a half in the pike position.
to be a bit further up the pecking order at the end of this competition.
Yeah, it's silver medalist four years ago.
Silver medalist back in 2004.
Fourth Olympic Games.
Truly exceptional athlete been through the mill in the build up to this one.
Plenty of injuries.
We'll talk more about that later.
That's not the start that Alex would be looking for.
Just tipping over a vertical as he enters the water there.
Maybe trying a little bit too hard.
Just a shame they're a little bit off.
I wonder whether he can bounce back.
Well, it's racing away as ever to uh compose his thoughts.
Get himself ready for round two.
Seventy-two is the score for day party which matches Mears and Warren in round one.
Elika Vasha with all that tape on his back.
You know, when we get a moment, we'll explain exactly what's holding him together.
Is it super glue?
Three point four is his opening gambit in with three and a half somersaults with tuck.
It's a big degree of difficulty to start with.
Oh it always makes the crowd take a little bit of an intake of air because the inward movement is the one where you are relatively close to the diving board.
Standing backwards, spinning forward, Kavash is actually, for me, a little bit too tight to the diving board.
And you see him going by.
He does a good job on it at the end.
It's 3.4 degree of difficulty.
So it will score a relatively good total points.
But the execution, he's tipping over a vertical there as he goes in.
Yeah, a little bit too close to the board for me.
The tape will hold him together.
That's his lower back injury he has.
More or less matching what he did in the semifinals.
78.20 for Kavasha.
We'll lift him because of that high degree of difficulty into second place.
Patrick housing of Germany.
Not quite so ambitious with his opening dive.
It's only 3.0 and we've seen it before.
It's that back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Oh, what a dive.
That is the best executed dive we've seen so far in this competition.
We are in the early stages, but what you're looking for here is great elevation from the diving board, beautiful pike shape, and he absolutely cruises it, slipping into the water with absolutely no splash.
8.5s, I think it's worth a nine.
Let's see what the judges think.
Well, for once, the judges disagree with the Leon Taylor.
They're not going to have any of that.
8.5 it is across the board.
We have the marks that count.
76.50.
Only one American remains in the lineup.
After problems for Chris Coolwell earlier in the competition.
This is Troy Doumay.
3.1 opener for him.
Forward three and a half somersaults in the pike position.
Oh, look at that entry.
Well, they sometimes think that no one actually went in.
There's not enough splash to fill a teacup.
As I've heard said many times before, Troy De May is certainly on fire.
Bronze medalist already.
This is going to get nines.
Well, she definitely should get nines.
Should be all over it.
look at that precision almost perfection just a little bit low on the water needed to be a little bit higher in my opinion for nine point fives and maybe in the even the elusive ten well that's uh throwing down the proverbial gauntlet isn't it lines across the board eighty three point seven zero with that uh degree of difficulty now y'all of mexico forward two and a half some sorts two twists three point four degree of difficulty
Oh the crowd like that because there's a lot going on so that's the forward two and a half with two twists you'll see a lot of the athletes using this yell game of tactics coming out with his big guns three point four here we are his one and a half somersaults well actually one then he comes out double twist he's a little bit stuck there so he does get it in it lands on his head it'll get eights and eight point fives look at the expression on his face as he goes into the double twist
He's been on fire yesterday and today and he continues to light the blue touch paper.
Yeah he's been the early leader on both occasions both in the preliminaries and our semi-finals and could well be the leader after the first round here with that 86.70.
On to the first of the two Chinese.
This is the one that missed out on a medal at the World Championships in Shanghai last summer.
It's Chin Kai's back.
Two and a half somersaults.
Three point zero.
You've seen it before.
Comes again.
That's more like it from Chin Kai.
Back two and a half, opting to open with his easiest dive.
Now some of the divers aren't, so it gives an unfair look at the scoreboard, because that's a beautiful dive.
Just saving it as he goes in, so bending at the hips, actually arching at the lower back and bending at the knees to try and stop the dive from going over a vertical, which he does a very, very good job on.
If he gets 80 points on this, it's a job well done.
80 and more, 81 points for Ching Kai, with three nines counting towards that total.
And he's off and running in third place.
Now, we've only seen one diver go above a hundred marks.
This is he.
It came in the final round of the semifinal this morning.
Not going quite so expansive early on, but it's not three point eight.
It's a three point four in with three and a half.
Oh, he means business this afternoon.
He was a bit shaky in the semi-final.
He was top qualifier for the semi-final.
Now, he has the demeanor of the great Dimitri Souten.
Can he emulate him?
Can he win Olympic gold today?
If he continues to dive like this, he'll certainly be in contention.
8.5s incoming for this amazing dive.
3.4, putting the pressure on the Olympic champion who's up next.
six points better than he managed in the semifinals earlier today.
Zakharov 85 just behind Castilla Fuerta and just ahead of Troy Dumay.
World champion, Olympic champion, three World Series wins this year in Moscow, Beijing, and Dubai.
Again, that's favored by many of the finalists.
Is that back two and a half somersault again, pike position three point zero.
Oh, it's not as good as you would expect from the Olympic champion.
You can see his teammates there just giving him a polite applause rather than standing up and whooping and hollering.
The aerial work is exceptional.
He's way above the five metre.
He's super flash, putting his feet right down at the water, cruising round, but he goes over a vertical.
I don't think that's worth more than seven point five, eight maybe.
And He Chong is off the pace.
Competition on.
yeah that expression tells you that he's not overly enamored with that 8.0 right across the board times the degree of difficulty will put him well at the moment not even in the top eight
That's how things look after the first round of dives.
A long way to go, yet five more rounds, remember?
Garcia Huerta again, leading the way early stages.
Zakharov, Dumay, Chinkai, and Ilya Kavashin, last name on that screen.
Then, Departee, Hechong, and Chris Mears, all with the same score as has Ethan Warren, and slightly tailed off, but not too much as Javier Garcia after round number one.
On to round two, in front of an expectant crowd, a very noisy crowd, a very enthused crowd who want to see the best diving.
And that's exactly what they're going to do in this Olympic final of the three meter springboard.
Ken Yeo.
His first ever final at the Olympics.
Going for a forward two and a half somersaults, two twists.
No, he's done okay.
His takeoff just letting him down a little bit.
Capturing all the footage, the coaches using the tablets there to instantly capture the dive.
Just a little bit back from the end of the diving board.
So when he comes out into his double twist here, he's falling a little bit too quickly.
And so it runs out of room a little bit.
It's still good.
I'm sure it will go over 75, seven halves and eights, which is a good dive, but wow, you know, this is the Olympic final.
78.20.
Good to see the coaches reading the instructions.
Take tablets with water.
Very good.
On to the Australian, Ethan Warren.
Equal eighth after first, but it probably doesn't mean an awful lot at this stage.
Four, three and a half semisaults with pikes.
Slightly moving up in terms of degree of difficulty.
3.1 this time instead of 3.0.
Oh, it's pretty good.
End of the dive, short of vertigo.
There's Matthew Mitchum, Olympic champion from Australia on the platform, whistling and cheering his 20 year old teammate on.
It's a fantastic job to get this far.
He just comes out of the dive a little bit early there, leaving it short as he entered the water.
So he won't go over 70 points on that and that will leave him off the pace already at these early stages.
I didn't expect him to be in the top six.
There we go.
That's fresh and says it all, doesn't it?
I love it because you know exactly what he thinks about a dive.
He doesn't hide his expressions or his emotions.
He knows a thumbs up and a smile to follow, but I think the initial expression told you what you need to know.
Javier Garcia forward two and a half, two twists.
Oh, that's a really, really good dive.
Now, I'm not sure what the judges are going to make of it.
He did move towards us here in the commentary box quite a lot, which gives the impression that the dive is, dare I say, skew-if.
Here we go.
He's spinning towards us, loses his legs a little bit.
The entry into the water is superb, but you can see he's moving towards us.
Now, if the judges spot that, they might penalise him.
If they don't spot it, he's going to get a big, big score.
Here he comes.
lovely entry into the water so judges have spotted today's spot is going a little bit erroneous halfway through no that's good marks 86.70 takes him into second place now the huge roar you heard not surprisingly to greet the arrival of Great Britain's Chris Mears second round dive reverse two and a halfs somersaults with pike for Mears
Oh, he's just let the dive go over.
He's obviously pumped full of adrenaline.
You see there's coach on the left, Lindsay Fraser.
He knows you get instant feedback.
Just toes over the end.
He was hanging ten, so he did well to wait.
Then he thought he was spinning slower than he was, but he's way up in the air over a vertical.
A little bit of a timber.
That's actually a bit of a blown dive there for Chris.
Such a shame.
He did all the hard work.
Yeah, dropped a few too many points I'm afraid.
That's not comparable with what he did earlier today.
58.50 for Chris Mears and that will put him at the bottom of the pack of those that have gone so far.
Alexander Dapati reversed two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists in the pike position, 3.3.
Oh, he's done really well, way back from the end of the diving board.
Such a shame, because if Alex is on the end of the diving board, this dive is all his.
But you can see him shaking his head as he gets out, because it's so difficult.
You've got to jump forwards and then spin backwards towards it.
One and a half twists, two and a half somersaults.
He might squeeze eights.
but I would expect to see nines from Alex if he wants to stay in the hunt for that third Olympic medal on the bounce in this event.
It's going to be tough out there for him today.
Well, a couple of judges quite liked it.
One judge will get the line through.
Eight point five will count towards the total on eighty point eight five for Alexander
It's the second round.
I could cause him some problems.
It's the begin.
It's forward four and a half somersaults with tuck 3.8 into the big tariffs early or you can say you can say, well, I think that might have been your fault, Bob.
You said it could
The problem started, the take off on this is oh so important.
He's on the corner of the diving board, means he can't push down with confidence, for he's lacking height, lacking rotation and running out of room.
He needed a 3.5 metre springboard, see him in right on the corner, left hand corner of the board.
Well, Kavasha off the pace as well.
Yeah, that's his big dive blown I'm afraid in terms of in fact, quite a spread on the marks there.
Four point five up to six.
They saw it slightly differently from a judging perspective but the marks aren't overly impressive for a high tariff dive.
Sixty-eight point four zero.
On to the remaining German, Patrick Housing for three and a half.
Three point one with Pike.
Maybe a little bit of a turn as he went into the water there.
I don't know whether the judges will spot that.
Let's have a look.
Spotting the water.
There he goes.
Out he comes in.
Yes, I can see both feet slightly there.
It shows me an overtwist but I think the judges might not see that or they tend to be letting those go a little bit.
Still, it's a very good dive.
Looking over to the coach for instant feedback.
Was that okay?
Am I a little bit over?
Yeah, I can feel
Is there an argument of having judges straight on as well as on the side as well so you could get a vision of that or a view of that?
No, the judging has always been from the side, it's trying to keep that stability.
Okay, just a thought.
Troy Dumay, reverse two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, 3.3 in the pike position.
or not quite as clean into the water as his first round dive but not far away at all yeah Steve Foley there high performance director for USA moved away from the the UK and has been working out there and look at this multiple medals for USA diving and Troy Demay
He's certainly in contention so far.
That's a big opening dive.
Backed up straight away with a very good second round.
Reverse one half, twisting two and a half.
Eighty-four.
Yeah, improvement on this morning as well as indeed both dives have been.
He's definitely in the credit column with an eighty-four point one five for Troy Dumais.
Now Huerta of Mexico.
Getting into the reasonably high tariffs now.
Not the 3.8.
Most of those come late on in the other programs.
In with three and a half somersaults with tuck 3.4 for Castillo, who is the current leader.
oh sounded like it was a women's tennis match there a little bit of grunting and groaning but it seemed to work for him swinging his arms depressing the diving board being patient waiting for the diving board to throw him back up up and away he's only very short when he gets in that shape he spins around like a dingbat if a dingbat spins around anyway in he goes zipping into the water with hardly any splash and that's a 80.85
Go on Yao.
I don't think David Atmar is in any danger, quite frankly.
After that last comment, 85 from Castillo Huerta, and it keeps him in first place.
Chin Kai of China, forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, pike position, 3.4 on the degree of difficulty.
Oh, steady, unfaltering and unwavering so far.
We see Chin Kai wobbling around a little bit.
in the prelims and the semis.
He seems pretty steady so far.
It's a little bit cornerboard there and he comes out four, two and a half, two twists.
It's three point four.
Needed to be good and that's certainly good.
Will he be catching up with the Mexicans lead?
I think he'd be closing it just marginally.
still a way to go yet.
Yeah, he is closing but hasn't quite reached it yet and they're still slightly behind Troy Dume but only by point one five of a point and that puts the Chinese, the first of the two Chinese into third place.
Ilya Zakharov second after the first round.
You know, he's got a big dive to finish off the program with.
This one not
Oh, he's gone and nailed it.
This is actually very impressive because he's the only diver actually up in the ante.
The backward group of divers, all of the others in this final, are doing a back two and a half in the pike position, playing safe with a 3-0.
Zakharov is going all guns blazing.
This is 3.5 degree of difficulty and he's absolutely drilled it.
This is going to sail over 80 points.
The gamble has paid off and the pressure lands firmly on the next divers shoulders.
Now, remember, we haven't seen any tens that count yet.
I think we might well do in the final.
Yeah, 91.
That's decisive.
That is a decisive dive from Zakharov.
38.5 multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
That's how you arrive with that figure.
That's actually 13 points higher than he did earlier on today.
That's massive.
Now He Chong, how does he respond?
Oh, he does respond, but not in the way that he would have liked to.
I'm not sure what the taping on the fingers is, those of you that are asking.
It's peculiar.
Normally, you see it on the toes because the board's quite abrasive.
Now, Heechong here really giving it some beans.
Look at him way above the five meter, almost as high as the 7.5 meter, but he goes over.
He overcooks it, if you will.
Look at him.
Can't even stop it.
It's so easy for him to adjust his suit when he went in there, which shows he was going over rotation.
All eights.
It's good.
but it's not good enough to take the lead.
Well, he only puts him in seventh place, someone from where he was, but here's the man of the moment and the man at the top of the standings, Ilya Zakharov from Russia has a about a five-point lead.
Well, they're about over Yanukovych, then Troy Dumay, Chinkai, Kenyo, good start from him, and Javier Garcia has moved off the bottom into sixth.
And here come the remaining divers.
Chris Mears, about 10 points adrift of Ethan Warren in 12th place.
Look at that.
Her Chong, world champion in seventh after two rounds.
Yeah, defending Olympic champion as well, of course.
So he knows what it's like to stand on that podium to win a gold at the Olympic Games.
But Zakharov, he's your man at the moment.
And believe you me, he's got some big, big dives to come.
Will they catch him?
Exciting stuff as we head into round three, six rounds in total, so this will represent halfway by the time all twelve divers have gone.
Ken Yeo in fifth place after round two, reversed two and a half with Pike.
Ooh, letting the dive go over as he went in.
I think he might have felt a little bit tight to the diving board so he stayed in his pike shape, a fraction too long.
Here you go, he's not too far away from the diving board so as he reaches back all over there, here comes the splash going back towards the diving board.
Not quite time to get your surfboards out but nearly.
Yeah, mistimed entry.
Spotted of course by the judges and indeed by us.
5.5 is where he gets across the board.
So less than 50, 49.50 and a very good start.
Has come to a rather abrupt end.
Now we're into the 3.8s again.
Ethan Moran going for it in round three.
Forward four and a half seven sorts with tuck.
Big degree of difficulty.
Obviously assigned to that a big risk.
If he comes off, looks great.
Oh, he does too.
The gamble's paying off.
There's his teammates on their feet.
The coaches are even impressed.
That must mean it's good.
3.8, this is his biggest degree of difficulty.
Almost on the end of the diving board.
Waits patiently, throws himself up in the air.
Just spotting the water as he goes in.
That's great.
Will it get over 90 points?
That's the question.
3.8 degree of difficulty.
So impressed with these divers.
20 years old from Australia.
Here come the scores.
Yeah, 91.20.
Highest score in the competition so far for Ethan Warren.
That leaps him up.
He's 11th place.
Can't be ranked 1 after that.
Here's Garcia.
Oh, just showing you how difficult that dive is.
He wasn't waiting around for Bob to introduce him.
So away he goes, looking to get the dive out the way.
Going for broke.
He didn't use this.
in the semi-finals here he is this is his big dive doesn't quite get into the tuck shape well enough little bit loose and so when he comes out he drops like a stone yeah what a shame there what an absolute shame into the hot tub to keep warm he knows his Olympic quest for a medal is over
Yeah, shake of the head, hands on hips.
And all the body language tells you that he knows he's just now playing for a decent spot at the end.
Chris Mears, lapping up the adulation, going for the reverse two and a half semisoles one half twisters the first of the upping the ante dives from Chris Mears.
After the two threes is a 3.3.
Oh, he had it on the takeoff.
Just playing a little bit safe as he went into the water.
He sailed over on his second-man diving.
Now he's just a little bit short on his third round.
Looked pretty good on the end of the diving board.
One-and-a-half twist into the two-and-a-half somersaults.
All looks good.
He just stops it a little bit short.
What a shame.
The splash being thrown away from the diving board.
A little bit too much of it.
Seven-and-a-halfs, I think.
Not quite as good as earlier.
No, a little bit behind the 8.
Some great expressions there, weren't there?
7.5 across the board for Chris Mears, times the degree of difficulty, 3.3, gives you 74.25.
Alex de Partiz, reversed 2.5 with Pike.
That's more like it now.
Are we gonna see the first perfect 10 that isn't very far away.
That's nine point fives It's very very good.
It needed to be Alex opting for a slight still doesn't look happy.
Come on Alex Give us a smile nine point fives.
I'm predicting that's an absolutely stunning reverse two and a half
Squeezing into that pike shape, looking where he's been rather than where he's going, points his toes towards the scoreboard and buries the entry.
Judges may be being a little mean on that.
Nines across the board, 81.
It's a good mark, very good mark, but could have been, should have been perhaps a little bit better than that.
It puts Departee into first place for the time being in the Cavashas.
Reverse two and a half, one and a half twists.
Oh, that's good from Kavasha just rolling over on his entry into the water just marginally.
The tape on the back obviously to support that area.
Divers get a lot of problems.
They are bending and moving themselves in such a ballistic and dynamic way.
Lots of aches and pains and injuries occur.
Training for long, long hours.
Kavasha being held together by sticky tape literally.
Anyway, he's made it through the prelims and semis and here he is in the final and that's one of his better dives.
We have the technology, we will rebuild it.
And they have 79.20 for Kavasha.
And up to third, he goes.
Patrick Housding now, eighth in Beijing.
So he finals at the Worlds in Shanghai last year.
3.9, this one.
Oh, it's worth shouting and screaming about.
Housding coming out, all guns blazing, moving himself up from the semi-final where he's doing this dive with two twists.
Busting out the big one now with a forward two and a half with three twists.
One, two, three.
He must be dizzy by the time he finishes that many twists.
He does a good job to get in.
That degree of difficulty is huge.
The execution is probably 7.7.5, but on a 3.9, that's going to get you 85 points plus.
Housding, wow.
incredible wow indeed and he's wowed the crowd and the judges with that 87.75 and housing with that kind of go for broke dive really has moved up into first place just ahead of alexander day party now here's another man who's
on form tonight.
Really has nailed his first two dives.
Number three coming up now.
Troy Dumay.
It's an easy one compared to the earlier ones.
A back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Only three point zero degree of difficulty.
Yeah, this is the dive, the weakest dive in Troy Dumay's list.
He used to open with it but he used to to leave him with too much to do.
Anyway, he's decided to move it to the middle of his program and it seems to be working much better there.
It's obviously still only
But if he's scoring more than eights, which he will on that, then that's a really good effort.
He might move him down the leaderboard, not because he didn't perform it well enough, but because of its low degree of difficulty.
We've seen some big dives going in and some big dives still to come.
Well, he's still hanging on in there.
He's in first place for the time being with that 76.50 and it's getting a bit bunched at the top, certainly with Dumais and Housding not much between them.
And here is the second ranked diver after round two, Castillo Huerta of Mexico.
Forward four and a half, here's that big one again.
Oh, Castillo's on the money.
This was his bogey dive.
Forward four and a half, 3.8 degree of difficulty.
And this one's so easy to make a mistake on.
He's back from the end a little bit, a couple of inches away.
But he up, up, and away.
He's so small, so compact that when he gets into that shape, he just spins and spins.
This is going to be big.
It's going to go over 90 points.
So it should too.
And Castillo, Mexico, on fire.
What a competition.
This is turning into 95 for Yael Castillo.
And he now has, would you believe, a 22-point lead over Doumei.
That's sizable at this stage of the competition.
Chen Kai has reversed three and a half somersaults.
The Chinese not quite yet in the groove or in top form, maybe now.
Oh, that's decisive!
Bob was laying it down there, not quite in the groove, and that is just slipped right into his groove.
My goodness.
Here we go.
Reverse.
Three and a half somersaults spinning backwards towards the diving board.
It's very easy to get disorientated, and he's absolutely buried the entry.
Hardly any splash.
Nine's 9.5s.
Just showing you the strain on the diver's body.
Wow.
Beautiful dive.
Are we getting some marks in this round or what?
Ethan Warren's 91, 95 from Castillo Huerta and now 96.25 from Chincay.
And he goes into second place, but not a million miles behind Castillo Huerta.
Ilya Zakharov, what do you have on this reverse three and a half somersault with tuck?
Oh, it's almost as good as Chiang Kai's, almost as good.
He's up higher than Chiang Kai's.
In fact, I actually like the dive more.
However, he just moves on the entry, just tips over a vertical ever so slightly.
He's going to get eight and a halfs.
He might get eight, eight, eight and a half.
It's not quite worth nines.
Oh, it's 90 points though.
There are thereabouts.
He's responding.
staying in contention yeah the marks it will count are eight point fives times that degree of difficulty you get eighty nine point two five boy is this competition hotting up hardly anything separating the top three and will become top four after we've seen her Chong surely
Reversed, three and a half, seven sorts with Tuck.
Three point five, just taking his time as he contemplates a very big dive.
He knows that eight and a halfs will put him back into the lead.
Oh, it's going to be there or thereabouts on eight and a half.
Isn't that interesting?
Chinkai, Ilya Zakharov, and He Chong, all of which, like for like, the reverse three and a half.
Chinkai laying down his marker and I think he won that round.
Heechong doing a great job there, just tipping over a vertical like Zakharov.
I think he'll pretty much get the same marks as Zakharov.
What does that do to the scoreboard?
Who is in the lead halfway through this exciting contest?
Well, it is not what we anticipated and saying Heechong not what he anticipated because he'll surely be thinking he's in for a medal.
Probably the big G, big G eluding him now.
Look at this after round three.
Yael Castillo Huerta, Ilya Zakharov, Chin Kai, Troy Dumay is about 19 points adrift.
Her Chong has a lot of ground to make up there.
Patrick Housding in six.
Finally, of course, the top three don't falter.
Departee on page two and Chris Mears bringing up the rear but closing in on Kenyo in 11th place.
This is a competition and we haven't seen the best of it yet.
The defending Olympic champion, removing himself from the hot tub, going back to his spot wherever he's sitting to compose himself halfway through the competition.
He's got some work to do.
And at the moment is not in a medal place.
Maybe not a very good place either.
Round four, Kenio of Malaysia, starting things off with a reverse two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, pike.
Oh, he's back into it with a sparkly one.
That's a good dive there from Kenny O.
Third round dive, fourth round dive.
He's got himself back up for it.
That's a great dive.
3.3 degree of difficulty this.
That'll get eights and eight point fives.
That's a very good dive, but he can't afford to make any mistakes.
No damage done in round three.
Forty-nine point five zero, which is not anywhere near what he required, but seventy-nine point two zero is.
Good reaction and a good comeback by Kenny O. Ethan Warren.
Eighth after round three.
In with three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Three point four for the Australian who likes to give us his immediate impressions on his dive as soon as he leaves the diving pit.
Let's see what he can do in round four.
Oh, he's backed it up.
His third round dive, the forward four and a half, sailed over 90 points.
This is slightly lower degree of difficulty, but I'd say this is going to get mid-80s.
Beautiful dive.
Waits patiently, goes into the water with hardly a ripple of splash.
You know what you're looking for now, and the judges certainly know what they're looking for.
And it's something along those lines.
Good work.
I'm looking for a smile and thumbs up.
Thank you.
86.70 for Ethan Warren didn't let me down and doesn't let himself down or Australia down for that matter and creeps into first place Javier Garcia with the reverse three and a half with tuck.
Oh, he's going for broke.
And I think his campaign is broken now, unfortunately.
Forward four and a half previously.
Short of vertical.
Yeah.
Raised eyebrows from the coaches.
And this one, the surf is definitely up.
Here we go.
Reverse three and a half.
Just hangs on into his tuck shape.
A little bit too long.
And over he goes.
And here comes the wave.
Get your surfboards out.
42.
Not my age, sadly.
Three fours.
Chris Mears came through the preliminaries in the final position moved up a couple of places run a few places actually to make that final and now finds himself in the final in round four with a forward two and a half somersaults two twists so again just a notch up on the degree of difficulty this is a 3.4 performed in the pike position
Oh, it's good from Chris.
I'm actually taken aback by the noise that this crowd generates.
It is quite extraordinary.
Yeah, he's holding his composure, making a slight error on his previous round dive.
That's good.
It's a little bit short as he goes in.
He does disguise it very well.
Maybe you'll sneak an eight or two from the judges.
It's straight up and down.
It is 3.4 degree of difficulty.
Could get close to 80 points.
These are the marks that count 8, 7.5, 7.5, 78.20 for Chris Mears not quite as aware of the camera as Ethan is.
Alexander de Patti round four in seventh after three in with three and a half somersaults with tuck three point four degree of difficulty.
Oh it's a good dive you can hear the cheers from the coaches who are just behind the judges.
He is a little bit over a vertical, but it's worth saying, six weeks ago, Alexandre Departee hit the diving board with his head on this dive.
He has 22 stitches or had 22 stitches on his forehead.
And this just showing the courage and the strength of character in this young man.
Silver medals too in this event in Athens and Beijing.
And he's here today to hang on to that Olympic dream.
I read somewhere the cup was 10.5 centimeters long.
Can you believe that?
83.30 for Departee, who departs.
Now on to Ilya Kavasha, position for the 3.5, reversed three and a half somersaults.
He currently finds himself in ninth and probably not challenging for a medal on this occasion.
Oh, his aerial work is very, very good.
Just fractionally over as he went into the water.
It's a big dive, and everyone's doing big dives.
This is so impressive.
Well, it is the Olympic final after all.
Wow.
Just consistently very good to get himself through.
Look at the strain and power.
Watching the knees come in, spinning around so quickly.
Pops his feet up, reaches back, just tipping over, but he does a good job saving it.
You get over 80 points for that.
82.25 remember all those marks with the line through do not count towards the total the ones without do times the degree of difficulty.
Now Patrick Housding with an in with three and a half semisorts with Tuck in sixth place after round three but it's very tight for the bronze medal position at the moment.
Oh, he just didn't quite get out of the dive quickly enough as he went into the water.
He's very tall as a diver.
So he does have to work a little bit harder to fit in all these rotations.
And technically, he is absolutely spot on.
Just a little bit low on the water here.
And you see him just straightening out as he's entering.
So I think he's only going to get sevens, 7.5s.
And that will put him slightly off the pace.
Yeah, it's waiting for confirmation on scoreboard.
Lowest score, joint lowest score he's had so far in four rounds.
And yeah, they're talking it over with the coach.
Smile to follow because he knows precisely what he has done.
Not a bad dive, but not quite what he hoped for.
76.50 Troy Dumais.
Can he be adding to the US medal tally in
the Aquatic Centre this week.
Both swimming, of course, very proficient and prolific and in diving doing pretty well too.
Inward three and a half somersaults with tuck for Dumé's fourth round dive.
Degree of difficulty 3.4 on this.
Oh, it's a decisive dive for Domaine.
He just fluffed it ever so slightly as he went in.
Just ever so slightly.
He's always low on the water.
He's not as strong as the other athletes.
Here we go.
Technically, he's over the diving board, a safe distance away.
You can just see here, a little bit short as he goes in, loses his feet, throwing up a little bit of splash.
Now, will the judges penalize him heavily?
Or will he sneak over 80 points if he does?
And good on him.
There's his family.
cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering, cheering,
Oh, the Mexicans are on fire.
I'm not surprised they're punching the air, so am I. Castillo, I thought he'd used up all his good dives in the prelims and semis and I'm pleased to say he's proven me wrong.
He's worked so hard, his consistency is so, so good.
This is a decisive dive.
It's the one that he could have wobbled on, and he's absolutely drilled it.
Is it 90 points?
It's going to be close to.
It's almost there.
86.7 first round, 85 second round, 95 third round, and fourth round dive 89.25.
Gives him a 30 point lead over Troy Dumais at this stage.
Wow.
Chen Kai in with three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
There's a lot of pressure on the Chinese here.
This is not going quite as we'd anticipated.
This is three point four with Tuck.
Oh, Ching Kai eating up the pressure.
I don't even know whether he knows it's in the arena.
Unfazed and unfaltering.
Inward, right over the diving board, squeezing into the tuck shape, cruising, piking out of it, showing the judges how easy it is for him.
This is going to be 90 points as well.
Look at the strength in those legs.
Absolutely precise.
Wow.
I think that's what we call game on now.
Game on.
Yeah.
91.801 and two separated by 0.20 of a mark.
I like.
Now does Zakharov like?
More to the point.
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists.
Is he going to put himself back in pole position after this?
Oh, yes, I think you will.
3.4, the same degree of difficulty that we've just seen from Chin Kai.
And this is the easiest of his last three dives.
And this is by no means easy.
Look how he just cruises, double twists, so much time.
If anything, he's just a little bit too far away from the diving board for nines.
But he should get 8.5s.
Let's see.
Judges might penalize because he is in the middle of the pool.
Should have swam to the far end.
Yeah.
Next bag.
I've got a time for us.
86.70 in third, but I'd say it's not a cast to drift third by any means.
three points behind silver exactly four points behind the leader who is still a Castillo Guerta by the way and He Chong fifth the world champion Olympic champion under a little bit of pressure here three point four in with three and a half somersault with
Oh, he hasn't responded.
He is a little bit off his game.
It just goes to show what the occasion could do to people.
He is feeling the occasion.
The defending champion is slightly off his game and you cannot be slightly off your game.
He is by no means out of it.
So Heechong is still very much in the hunt for medals.
But he's certainly not way out in front where he's accustomed to being just tipping over a vertical.
It's going to get eights and eight point fives, but he would have needed nines and nine point fives to keep up with the pack.
Well, interesting.
Well, very interesting because he got eighty five.
He has to make up twenty eight points to get gold right now.
Twenty eight points.
Is he going to do that?
No, unlikely unless people make mistakes.
He could end up at the medals and that would be a shock.
Here's how it looks after round four.
This is thrilling.
It's very entertaining, and we're on the edges of our seats.
Hope you are, too.
Look at that.
Hardly four points.
Well, exactly four points, actually, both of you, using your fingers and toes between one and three.
And then the world and Olympic champion struggling for medals.
Chris Mears off the bottom.
Into 11th place.
Crown have just seen that on the scoreboard.
And any finish above 12th.
Well, it's happy to be in the final, of course, but any progress he can make up that leaderboard, he'll be delighted with.
That's what it is.
That's where we are.
London 2012, which has been a roaring success in pretty much every department.
Certainly has been for the Chinese, who have won every gold medal in diving so far.
But at the moment, they're not.
Start of the penultimate round of the men's three meter springboard final.
It is wide open for the middles and it's not being dominated by the Chinese at this stage.
Ken Yeo with his penultimate dive in with three and a half somersaults with Tuck with 3.4 on the degree of difficulty.
Yeah, it's one of Ken's trickier dives.
His biggest degree of difficulty at 3.4 and he's done a very good job with it.
He's coming down off that extraordinary high at the end of the last round there.
We're seeing the big guns going at each other.
Ken bringing us down to some kind of reality but that is a very well executed dive.
Lots of people asking about the cloth that divers seem to use.
It's actually called a shammy.
Sammy Lee, who invented the Sammies, is actually here competing in the 1948 Olympic Games to dry off the divers in between drives, keep them warm so their muscles don't get too cold, but also to dry their hands and shins so they can hold on to those shapes.
Hope that makes sense at home.
That's where Sammy the Shammy came from then.
Exactly.
76.50 for Kenyo with his fifth round dive.
Second up is Ethan Warren of Australia who's not out of it yet, you know, he's sixth place.
A couple of very good dives.
Here comes the reverse three and a half.
Oh, he sneaked it in as well with hardly a ripple of splash.
Very good.
He's certainly upped his game.
He's a bit here and there in the prelims and made it through.
Oh, manages to stop himself falling back in the pool.
Wow.
He certainly didn't fall in the pool on this one.
Just twenty years old from Australia.
First saw him a couple of years ago in the Commonwealth Games in Delhi and I was ultra impressed now and he isn't failing to deliver here in this final.
Wow.
Good balance.
89.25.
Now, he's going for a bit of a run as well because save your energy, boy.
These guys are ultra fit.
Don't look at me when you say that, please.
Ethan Warren them to the top of the pile for the time being.
He is Javier Ilana Garcia, who's race is run, I'm afraid.
12th place for him.
Would like to move up a spot or two if he can with this in with
Oh, the wheels have come off and they're bouncing down the street now.
Not to be caught, unfortunately.
A real shame.
That's three poor dies from Javi.
Yeah, this is what happens sometimes.
You lose it.
Diving is very much like that.
Sometimes when your head's not in it, over rotating.
Loads of splash coming up into the hot tub.
And yeah, I don't know where I am.
I don't know what's going on.
I feel like I'm over the shot.
Tough day.
Yeah, and the marks weren't making him feel any better either.
I don't think they appeared on your screen, funny enough.
3.5s.
And not quite what he was hoping for with that.
The total mark 35.70.
Now Chris Mears, his fifth round dive, got two big ones to finish.
in with three and a half somersaults tuck three point four degree of difficulty oh he's just done the same as Javi just before him overcooked it just staying in his tuck shape a little bit you can see on the expression he knows instant feedback when the water smacks you in the lower back and the back of the legs all the aerial work is very very good just hanging on a little bit you can see him tipping over there it's another surfboard moment
What a shame for me.
Look at that.
Right over the diving board.
Aerial work is excellent.
Just waiting too long before he lets go and over he goes.
Timber.
56.10 is the mark which now will be confirmed for you on screen.
5.5 across the board.
It's slightly better and it looks like he won't finish in 12th place.
Alexander Departee.
Forward four and a half.
This is his big dive.
Doesn't normally do this one.
oh he's giving it a good go and just unfortunately letting it roll over there's his mum and dad there here to support him he's going for broke just see him shaking his head he knows he's just let the dive go not seeing him do this on the springboard certainly hasn't competed it here at these olympic games just rolling over as he goes in he's only going to get six and a halfs or sevens that is day party's campaign for a medal over unfortunately what a shame but an absolutely incredible athlete
Well, he gave it a go and I like to see athletes do that.
There's no point holding back.
It's an Olympic final.
You've got to go for broke because the competition is so severe and so fierce as is being proved today because in here, Kavasha is not in the mix at all anymore.
Back two and a half summer slots with Pike for the man from Ukraine.
It's been an ultimate round dive ninth after round four.
Oh, it's tidy.
It is a low degree of difficulty.
The game of tactics electing to use his lowest degree of difficulty now when everyone are bringing their their big dives out the higher degree of difficulties.
So, it's probably seven, seven and a half, maybe an eight.
So,
Lovely slow motion camera work, isn't it?
Just bringing the dives to the viewer.
67.50, a selection of 7.5 marks for Ilya Kavasha.
Patrick Housding, 3.5 degree of difficulty.
Eighth after round four, step down a bit, reverse three and a half for the remaining German.
Oh, he comes out, all guns blazing on that one.
Yeah, I think it deserves a bit more applause than that.
That was superb.
Just faltering slightly on his previous round, the inwards, this reverse, absolutely spot on.
Diving both springboard and platform.
Long, long training hours for this young man, but he seems to be able to take it all in his stride.
Quite tall for a diver.
That's his biggest, biggest dive, highest scoring dive so far.
Well over 90 points, I guess.
You guessed correctly.
Here comes confirmation that you're spot on.
Ninety-four point five zero all nines.
Times the degree of footy gives us ninety-four point five zero.
Now, Troy Doumay.
Three point five.
Yeah, it's a reverse three and a half once again.
Tough position for the American and a tough position for him because he's in fifth place.
Troy just didn't quite rip the entry.
Such a shame.
I thought that that was going to be just what could prove critical this.
Troy slightly off the pace.
He stayed with the diving board, didn't skip off.
He's done all the hard work and just rolls over.
Doesn't quite keep the splash down.
It's going to get eight.
But he would have needed well over 90 points to stay in contention.
I think that will leave him just a little bit off the pace.
Yeah, a couple of points behind Patrick Housding.
It could mean that Troy Dumet slips and drops.
One more position now.
Here is our current leader.
All the pressure.
Can he keep this fantastic run going?
It's an easy dive though.
He's going to lose some points here.
He will back two and a half somersault three point zero.
This has to be absolutely spot on.
The others will be catching him after this.
Oh, it's good, but you know, this is the game of tactics.
Yel's come out, flexing his muscles, doing all his big dives early and absolutely nailing them now.
This is his lowest degree of difficulty and it's probably his weakest dive so far, just arching into his back there.
It's only going to get eight.
It's going to get, what, 72, 73, 75 at best with that back arch as he goes in.
Now, the other boys are going to go and stick a 90 points plus on the board, and that's going to shake it up at the standings.
Well that's good enough to keep him in first place for now but the question is how much longer can he remain in pole position because there's some big big dives coming up including this one 3.8 went disastrously wrong for Ching Kai in the prelims got it right in the semis though forward four and a half somersaults 3.8 with tuck this could be a hundred points or more if he gets it right
Oh, he's just out a little bit early.
That is a very, very good dive.
Oh, it's an outstanding takeoff.
He's up in the air, completing the dive almost effortlessly.
Sorry, try and get my words out in the excitement.
Oh, that's a shame.
I thought it was going to be the one.
He's out a little early, a little short vertical as he goes in.
It's going to get him well over 90 points, as I mentioned, that could shake up the leaderboard.
Oh, if he'd have waited in his shape just a fraction longer, we'd have seen him go over 100 points.
As it is, it's 96.908.5 will count the scores with the lines through them, as ever do not.
And that puts him 25 points clear of Castillo Huerta.
But Ilya Zakharov has some points to make up.
Oh, my goodness me.
Oh, that is phenomenal.
You should stand up in the crowd because we are witnessing something truly extraordinary.
Very hard to please the Russian coaches, as you can see, but it's not very difficult to please me.
That's going to go nearly 100 points.
It's 3.9, a forward two and a half with three twists.
You are the man.
My goodness me, Zakharov.
Wow.
Well, do you know what?
He's not quite the man.
99.45.
The gap between one and two is now 1.25 points.
Oh, game on.
Come on, Heechong.
What have you got in your toy box?
Chinkai and Zakharov are separated by 1.25 points going into the final round.
And there's another Chinese who might have a little bit of a say about the outcome of this competition.
He is Heechong forward four and a half.
Is he aiming for 100 points?
It's time to shake it all up.
Oh, he is too.
He needs 100 points and that is going to be very far away at all and I can safely say I'm not disappointed.
Look at that, Zakharov.
He's not even bothered.
No point in looking at what you can't control.
Let them get on with it.
All I can do is concentrate on my next dive and He Chong is soaking up this pressure.
Easily completes the dive.
Maybe just a fraction over a vertical.
So, oh, I don't know.
Where's he going to be?
He did have some points to make up, so he's certainly not going to be top of the leaderboard.
Fourth.
Not in the medals yet.
But he's one point behind the medals.
Wow.
That's how tight this competition is.
It is unbelievably close for both one and two and three and four.
Just look at this.
Four fifty-two plays four fifty-one.
Four twenty-seven plays four twenty-six.
That's how it looks for the medals.
I think that's where the medals are going to go.
But who's going to get what?
Patrick Housting in five.
Troy Dumay in six.
We've got three point nine coming at me.
I'll talk you through the final round dies of those top four as you share with us who's at the back.
Yeah, Chris Mears in 11th place still, and Ken Yeoh just above him in 10th.
No medals today for Warren Departee or Kavasha.
So the battle for the bronze between, or it looks like the battle of the bronze between Castillo and Heechong.
So you've got a 3.7 versus a 3.9.
So it's pretty much dive for dive.
The interesting thing is Ching Kai and Ilya Zakharov.
Chinkai only has a 3.3 versus Zakharov's 3.8 that he scored 100 points on in the semifinals.
Oh, come on.
Boy, oh boy, is this a competition or is this a competition?
It is as tight as a drum for first and second and third and fourth, and we are loving it.
These are the support players we'll see first though in round number six.
The final round for Kenyo, his last competitive die before retirement is a back two and a half summer sorts with pike three point zero degree of difficulty.
And thanks for all your contributions, Ken.
What a dive to finish his career on second Olympic Games Getting fine support there from his teammates did so well to make this final and this what a final to dive in as well Wow, and he gets to open it up.
He's the first diver to complete all six dives It's a fine job to finish And I'm sure you move to coaching waving to the crowd
enjoying his time out here.
Why don't Kenny O?
75 and goodbye Ken with 8.5s and eight.
Certainly a nice way to bow out.
11 more to go.
Ethan Warren for Australia.
He's battled well.
He's dived well for the most part.
He's not going to be featuring in the medals.
How high can he get up these standings?
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, 3.4 degree of difficulty to finish off for the Australian.
And he'll perform this in the pike position.
What a terrific set of dives this young man from Australia has performed.
Shouting and cheering from Matthew Mitchum still to perform.
Olympic champion himself appreciating his teammates efforts here and he's done a really really sterling performance.
Great job at the beginning of the field.
He's going to get close to 500 points and that is incredible.
Let's see what the final score is for Ethan Warren.
It is 488.95, 81.6 on the final dive.
Yeah, it is.
Other competitions may well have won it.
All got a silver medal, but the competition's so fierce and so intense here.
81.6 and 488.95, not quite enough.
Probably silver spoonest today, but he's come through a pack of 29 to get into the 12.
Here's Javier Garcia.
Just putting the reception and the applause on the crowd.
Let's it die down before they reverse.
One and a half somersaults, three and a half twists.
You wouldn't have seen this by anybody else.
All right, so relatively good dive for Javi to finish.
He did struggle on his previous few rounds, but as Bob was saying, great that he's here.
Teammates from years ago there from the Spanish team waving to the crowd.
He's thanking their support.
This is old school.
One and a half somersaults, three and a half twists.
So good dive to finish on for Javi.
He'll take his learnings away.
Still got some life left in him, I'm sure.
We'll see him back again.
And the mark, which the crowd are privy to.
You are now 81.60 for Javier Ilana Garcia, three eights.
And that is him done.
now final dive and he has acquitted himself brilliantly over three rounds and hasn't let anybody down and we'll be back for more world championships next year commonwealth games in 2014 and the next olympics we hope his body holds together for rio chris mears this is his big one to finish you see it by other people how will he do
on the forward four and a half somersaults with tuck three point eight top of the shop for him.
Oh, what a dive to finish on.
That's exactly what he did in the semi-finals.
There's his mum and dad and family.
They should be oh so proud.
And I certainly am too, here in the Comerty Box.
Such a nice guy.
What a dive to finish on.
I thought, after the semi-finals, will he match it in the final?
And he has saved the best until last.
This is 3.8.
He goes oh so high.
Cruising, dipping into the water, marginally over a vertical.
Beautiful rip entry.
Congratulating Ethan Warren there.
These divers are all great mates as well.
Such a good sport.
Coached by Lindsay Fraser in Southampton.
Let's see what he gets for the marks.
Here they are.
Whoa, 100.7.
Steady on Bob, you've deafened me.
That's 10 better than he went in the semi-finals.
91 in the semi-final.
100, nearly 101.
In the final.
Goodness me.
Chris Mears, you have a future in this sport.
Boy, if you didn't already know that.
Dramatic.
He extrode me.
Well done, Chris.
Now from the youngster, obviously to the old master a little bit.
Still looks quite youthful.
Still has plenty to give to Alex Daparte.
Forward two and a half with two twists.
Oh, you gave him the commentator's curse.
He had exactly what happened to Jack Law yesterday in the prelims.
Oh, the knee trembler, the knee buckle.
I'll show you on the replay.
He's gone for the big one.
His knees have just given out.
And the diving board, it's unbelievable that he managed to complete the dive.
He will get some marks on that.
Wow, drama in this last round.
Look at his knees just give out there.
Nothing you could do about that.
Oh, what a way.
Yeah, he's worked so hard to get here, hit his head on the diving board six weeks ago and that's not the way that he wanted to end his Olympic campaign here in London.
I don't think there's anything really that we haven't seen in this competition preliminaries, semi-final or final.
It's been full of unbelievable drama.
Now we're into that suspense about who's going to get the medals.
It won't be this man, Ilya Kovashchev, though he thought he had the pedigree to do so, to push for it at least, but hasn't quite worked out for him.
Forward, two and a half somersaults, two twists, 3.4 in the pike position for his final dive.
There you go, Kavasha showing you how the dives should be done.
Daypartee struggling, buckling at the knees.
Kavasha staying with the diving board, using it rhythm-wise.
Here we go.
Up he goes.
One and a half somersaults out into the double twist.
Down into the pike.
He's done a reasonable job today throughout, hasn't he, Kavasha?
Three limbs, semis, and here in the final.
Middle of the pack, I think, in the end.
Maybe just above Mia's.
Let's see.
The mark is 86.7.
Yeah, 86.7 confirmed on the screen.
8.5.
So he does move above Chris Mears.
And just behind Ethan Warren.
Actually quite a long way behind Ethan Warren in the end.
26 points behind the Australian.
Sharp end of the competition, but probably not sharp enough for Patrick Housding to get there.
This is big.
It is big.
It's three point seven.
Reverse two and a half somersaults, two and a half twists for the German.
Oh, how did he manage that from the fulcrum end of the diving board?
He's way back from the end of the diving board and he has to do one of the most complicated dives possible.
Look, he's way back from the end.
He has to lean right over the diving board.
Oh, and he still moves it away a safe distance and manages to drill the entry.
Wow, I'm running out of superlatives.
Truly terrific.
It's astonishing how he managed to do that.
I would give him extra points because he was nowhere near the end of the diving board.
3.7.
It's going to get over 90 points.
It does.
94.35.
505 total.
Also define the laws of gravity.
Yeah.
505.55.
If you get over 500, you expect to get a medal normally, and he probably won't today.
Troy Dume.
Again, enjoying the attention, enjoying the crowd noise, and it has been absolutely fever-pitching here tonight.
Last dive, 3.4.
Again, forward two and a half somersaults, two twists.
Dumay trying to get the top five finish if he possibly can.
It'll be hard.
Oh, he finishes on his best dive, he always favours this and that's as good as it gets for Troy Demay.
Just a little bit off the pace, not because of his dive, just maybe lacking a little bit of degree of difficulty, but he's going to go close to 500.
Will he nip over it?
I'm not sure, it's going to be close, but that is a beautiful dive to finish.
The all-important entry into the water, hardly a ripple of splash as he goes in.
Yep, there's his mum and dad.
They like it, and I certainly like it.
Well done, Troy.
There we are, shown his appreciation.
Already won an Olympic medal here.
Just a little shy of the 500 mark, but only just.
88.40 takes him to 498.35.
And for the time being, into second.
Now, how much pressure?
Oh, that was a little nervous look, wasn't it?
Wasn't it just?
Oh, here you go.
How much pressure?
Oh, he's looking up and everything.
No.
Is there on Yal Castillo Huerta?
At the moment, he is in bronze medal position, but there is no room for maneuver and no room for error.
This has to be absolutely spot on for a medal, you'd think.
Reverse two and a half somersaults, two and a half twists.
Could he pick up another Mexican medal at the Olympic Games?
Oh no, he has opened the door to none other than Heechong.
Heechong, there he is.
He knows all he needs to do.
His nail is last diving and medal is his.
Yao, five out of five in his last dive.
He's gone for the big one.
This is reverse two and a half, two and a half twist.
He just skips off the diving board a little bit aggressively there, leaving himself too much to do and he lands on his shoulders.
Now that's throwing up a lot of splash.
He could get taken out by Housling and Dumé, maybe, but I think he had enough buffer.
What an absolute shame.
He's gone for broke.
He has gone for broke.
He didn't use this in the semis.
He went for it in a big way.
Maybe it's going to see him blow out.
Oh, and it does.
Oh, he's dropped down below Housling and Dumé.
Wow.
Oh no, after so much good work, five pretty much impeccable rounds, 86, 85, 95, 89, 72, bit down on that, and 64.
Jinkai, current leader.
And it's got pressure on him from Zakharov, so he has to get it right.
Everybody needs to be right on their game now.
Reverse two and a half.
Only 3.3, remember?
Oh, only 3.3, but apart from that little bit of splash, it's absolutely brilliant.
technically needed to be spot on which it was he landed on the end of the diving board no mistakes here on the takeoff one and a half twist folds into that pike shape and apart from this little bit of splash that's a perfectly vertical entry i don't think he's going to get much change out of nines maybe the judges will go with him and give him nine point fives and that puts the pressure firmly on
Zacharoff, the only diver.
Two divers to go.
Jinkai loves it.
Shaking his fist.
How much does he like it?
How much do the judges like it?
89.10.
I make it.
Zacharoff has to get 91 with his dive to overtake him.
in the region of 91 now 541 I just written that down just to make sure 541 now what can this man do he needs 90.4
90.4 required to win for Ilya Zakharov it's a 3.8 he did this perfectly this morning forward four and a half somersaults with tuck
Oh, he's done it!
That's gold for Russia.
That is definitely gold for Russia.
China have not had it all their own way.
Look at the British team jumping up there.
They are appreciative of this super special Russian diver.
He is the Olympic champion.
I can tell you before the scores come up.
That's unbelievable.
What a dive to finish on.
Probably goes to 100 points like he did in the semi-finals this morning.
I take my hat off to you, Zakharov.
You are the man.
We're waiting for the mark.
The crowd are waiting for the mark.
He's waiting for the mark.
just confirmation surely of a Russian goal he's done it again he's done it again even better than before no perfect 10s will count sadly because that would have put the tin lid on it and confirmed but 104.50 that is immense and impeccable
555.90.
That is in a completely different stratosphere in this competition.
I cannot believe what I'm just seeing there.
Zakharov stops the Chinese gold rush.
Or does he?
Yeah, of course he does.
It's impossible for He Chong to get anything better than bronze, but that is wide open for him now.
Wide open.
And Chong needs 80.
Really?
If my calculations are right, he needs 80.
So providing this goes well, 3.9 degree of difficulty.
That should take him comfortably sailing over that mark.
Yeah, that'll get him there.
Because it's such a big degree of difficulty, he's been a little bit off his game today.
Yeah, no danger for you, Zakharov.
You are the Olympic champion.
He Chong, that is good enough for bronze.
Gold, four years ago.
Long time, four years.
This is the triple out for a two and a half, three twist.
It's a big degree of difficulty.
3.9.
He Chong will see himself on the podium, but not in the position he wanted to be.
Qualified top for this final.
Ends up being beaten by his fellow countryman, Chin Kai.
and the truly outstanding Ilya Zakharov.
The world champion is no longer the Olympic champion, 97.50.
It is good enough for third and no better for He Chong and
The old order has been overturned.
China have won five golds.
They're not going to win six in a row because Ilya Zakharov has done it again with the most immense sixth round dive with 104.50.
Oh, look at Chink.
He's giving it his all.
Look at that 541 and that's not good enough to win the gold.
Look at this elation and devastation.
The camera just cut from one to the other.
Someone achieves their dream and another one loses it all in the same
Let me just give you the sequence of marks for Ilya Zakharov.
85, 91, 89.25, 86.70, 99.45, 104.50.
Now perhaps he knows how the rest of them feel because it's always Chinese gold, or seems to be anyway, but not this time around.
The world champion is not the Olympic champion.
Amazing scenes here at the diving point.
You see Chin Kai there in tears.
This is how much it means to these athletes.
What a treat for the spectators here to watch that.
Now let me just tell you, 555.
That is unbelievable.
I have never seen diving like that.
just 21 years old, Ilya Zakharov.
I don't think he's going anywhere for a bit.
Looks a little bit like Dmitry, the great multi-Olympic gold winning medalist from Russia.
His hero.
And I'm not surprised.
He walks like him, he talks like him and he certainly dies better than him, dare I say.
What an athlete and what a contest.
Well, I don't think that smile's going to come off his face for a little while, and nor should it.
That is amazing.
21 years of age.
Didn't even come close to dropping a dive in that sequence of six.
And China have to settle and be satisfied with it.
They're not, of course, as you can tell by their expressions, with silver and bronze, because that gold is returning to Russia.
I don't think he can quite believe it.
The crowd are delighted to see something a little bit different that in the diving pool and plenty of support.
That one obviously in the Kavash's support group are now adopting.
They can't get the T-shirts made up that quickly, unfortunately.
Ilya Zakharov.
is the winner.
Five five five point nine zero.
It's just as amazing as I'm saying.
I can't believe it.
One, two, three, Patrick housing missing out by almost twenty marks on the bronze.
Troy Dume Castillo who threw it away.
Last time through a chance of a medal away.
And where did Chris Mears finish in the end?
Look, he's made it up to ninth place with that terrific last dive.
That's where he came in and that's where he goes out in ninth place, 439.75.
His day will come again and he'll be much further up the pecking order next time.
Right, deep breath time, everybody, because that is astonishing.
We've kind of been building up the 10 meter as the big climatic event of these Olympic Games in diving.
But I tell you what, the 10 is going to take some going to beat that, is it not?
Well, let's just wait and see.
We have been treated to, well, just contest after contest of the, well, the highest performances.
There's some, well, there was all sorts in that competition from start to finish, wasn't there?
So, you know, the platform is the Blue Ribbon event.
The women start tomorrow evening in the preliminaries and then the men get to close late on Saturday night, local time.
and I'm just taking each dive at a time and each contest at a time because it is an absolute treat.
I've been involved in this sport since, you know, I was eight years old and it just gets better and better and better and I hope you're enjoying it all over the world because we certainly are here, we've got a best seat in the house, we've also got two microphones to bring it alive so I hope you're enjoying it as much as we are.
Does Ilya Zakharov have ice running through his veins?
Now, there you're in a situation, you know, that you got your biggest dive to come, you know, if you do it well, you're Olympic gold medalist, but there was no sign of nerves.
He bettered what he did in the semifinal.
We thought that was pretty exceptional.
He's actually gone beyond that.
Yeah, well, that's what two true champions, you know, become Olympic champion by not being able to hold it together in the greatest arena that there is, you know, this gladiatorial out there.
There's everyone staring at you.
You're standing there on the diving board.
All those years and years and thousands and thousands of dives in training come down to this one moment in time, one dive at a time.
each of those six dives counts and it's important that you nail all of them so Yael Castillo my heart goes out to him because that final dive he went for broke that was a big dive he upped the ante did an even more complicated dive than he did in the semi-finals he went for broke and unfortunately he broke he didn't do it he didn't nail it and he ended up outside the medals
whereas Ilya Zakharov from the start opened up with his easiest dive and his easiest dive is 3.4 degree of difficulty that is normally your most difficult dive he is a cut above and what an amazing performance and to do it here when it counts and score 555 that is well
Unbelievable.
Can we be a little bit parochial for a little while?
Those around the world, I hope you won't mind our self-indulgence a bit.
Only two divers went over 100 today.
One of them was British.
Yeah, very good from Chris.
You know, he's got a lot of work to do on his list and his consistency.
the reverse two and a half somersaults in the second round led him down otherwise he'd have been even higher up 439 is a very very good score but what he has shown is bursts of brilliance and that was in the end of the semi-final to secure his berth in this final and then he finished up in a real treat for the home crowd wasn't it i can't believe how noisy it is in here i think i get used to it and then i get surprised every time a member of team gb stands on the diving board and i could only begin to imagine what it might be like as the week goes on
fantastic support in here people are loving their diving we're getting a lot of love on twitter from around the world so thank you for that and we'll continue to work hard to bring it alive and explain some of the nuances and idiosyncrasies of the sport but the divers are doing all the talking aren't they my goodness me we don't have to do very much at all when the diving is that good
from the from the home athletes as well as all of these fantastic divers from all around the world and you know let's go through it again that is the first gold that hasn't gone to China in the 2012 Olympic Games in the diving pool now that is quite something everyone was you know predicting a clean sweep and it's been stopped on event number six
Actually, I think this is the one that most people thought was the strongest the whole lot, wasn't it?
Yeah, one of the strongest.
You know, I wouldn't ever underestimate Zakharov and he split the Chinese last year in Shanghai.
So I'd say they're probably dominance is stronger in the women's events than the men's.
I think the men's is more open.
Maybe, you know, dare I say the close event, the Blue Ribbon event, the men's platform, you know, is the door open.
The rest of the world believe.
And, you know, if you can do it, I can do it.
Just going back to Chris Mears for a moment before we move on to other things.
4.61 in the semi, 4.39 in the final.
He actually dropped down by 22 but actually finished in the same place so in terms of position exactly the same.
Will he be a little bit disappointed he's not better than what he did in the semi when when marks do tend to be a bit higher in the final generally?
Yeah of course he made some mistakes the second round dive as I highlighted in our previous conversation you know he was down on that a few other
slight errors but uh you know his job was to make it to the final and enjoy it and that's exactly what he did he handled the occasion he handled himself you know superbly under the pressure under the expectation he smiled he enjoyed it and he let his dive in do the talking he's only 19 years old he's got a lot of years ahead of him oh what a fantastic first olympic experience fifth in the synchronized uh springboard event and then he's come out and nailed it ninth in his individual wow
I take my hat off.
Very good indeed.
Well done, Chris Mears.
How are you feeling for your good mate, your very close friend Alex Departee?
He didn't quite finish or go out the way he wanted to.
Yeah, tough day at the office for Alex.
You know, he's had a really tough four years, injury after injury after injury.
Never really seemed to get back into his rhythm and really start to shine after his silver medal in Beijing.
and that's sometimes what happens he's been the top of his game since he was 13 years old way back in 1998 and here today you know just goes to show it can happen to anyone his last round dive instead of getting 82 plus which is what we normally expect maybe even in the 90s when he's on his game he got 22 points
and he's very fortunate to get that.
He had a complete knee buckle and we saw what happens yesterday in the preliminaries.
Jack Law had a complete knee buckle and didn't even manage his dive, completely failed the dive.
And we saw Stefan Fek, who slipped off the diving board.
So, you know, it happens to everyone, including Olympic silver medallists from the previous two games.
of course, my heart goes out to him.
Um what a truly extraordinary athlete.
Maybe he'll, you know, retire after this.
It's uh you know, I'm sure that's his decision and his announcement to make.
Um I certainly want to be speaking for him.
I know that he would have wanted to go out on a high.
So, let's wait and see.
See how he feels.
See what options he's got but he's, you know, world champion, Olympic silver medalist.
He's got absolutely everything under his multiple Commonwealth medalist.
He's got everything under his
that.
Let's talk about the young guns.
We've mentioned Chris Mears.
What about Ethan Warren?
I think he's impressed you, impressed you at the Commonwealth Games.
It was pretty consistent again tonight.
Yeah, he was.
Absolutely.
He's just got better and better.
He's turned up the, you know, turned it up each time.
So, prelims, he was in the mix.
Semifinals, he moved up further into the mix and then final.
What did he end up with?
Four eighty-eight.
It's a big score.
I mean, it's it's shadowed by the what would he come seventh?
Yeah, the top six were right out there.
Four eighty-eight.
You
Well, not today.
Not in the London Olympic final.
Four divers over 500.
Have we ever seen that before?
Well, not in Olympic games for sure.
Maybe in a in a Grand Prix around the world when the judging is more elevated, you might see.
That's why we don't have world records in diving because the judging scores vary.
It depends, you know, how much of a
how much guidance they're given out the back sometimes the powers that be would say okay judges you need to be really strict on this particular element of the dive so if you see anyone with a split tuck shape that's a tuck shape with their knees wide apart make sure you penalize them and you know it depends and that can really influence the marks I think the judging here has been very consistent though Bob
Normally we have a bit more of a rant about the judging but I think here, well I haven't heard you rant once actually about the judges.
Well I think we did, I think we did.
Maybe once or twice you've had one but I've certainly been very comfortable with the judging you know there's you know the measures are in place they take away the two highest and the two lowest to leave the three middle scores trying to average it out all the time in the synchro even more complex but the intention is to try and give to take away that subjectivity as much as they can and try and
average out the scores before it is of course multiplied by the degree of difficulty and boy oh boy did we see some degrees of difficulty here and all this week and more to come of course with the with the platform events to finish off this extraordinary olympic games are we going to see fours or 3.9 as far as it's going to go
Well, they're, you know, they're mathematically calculatable if there's that's a made up word there.
But, you know, yeah, you can look at it.
It's almost like a computer game.
If you can fit the spins in, there's a degree of difficulty which will go next to it.
But at the moment, three point nine, that's pushing the ceiling as far as I'm concerned.
Well, we've been living off the ceiling and on the ceiling during the course of the evening.
And we're just about to come down to terra firma after what we've just seen.
Because, yeah, you got it right.
If you just tuned in, in the center of your screen is not a Chinese diver.
Yes, to your left and to your right.
But position number one is occupied by a Russian.
And how often do we see this when the presentation parties obviously agreed in advance?
This happens all the time.
They suspect it'll be a Chinese gold, and it's not a Russian that can present it.
The Chinese presentation party are ready with also some assistance from Margo Mountjoy, executive board member of the governing body for water sports around the world.
Swimming, diving, water polo, open water and synchronized swimming, which is also taking place in this very pool.
That's the presentation party.
It seems to me that Ilya Zakharov cannot wait to stand on that platform.
He's jumping around like a hyperactive kid.
I'm not sure you'll see much of a smile from He Chong.
The world champion.
An Olympic champion from Beijing can't muster a smile because bronze is not what he came here for.
And he would have thought if somebody said to him, right, you're going to get 524.15 points.
He said, yeah, that's fine.
I'll take that because that's going to be a gold medal.
Not on this occasion.
It wasn't really good enough for bronze.
In fact, he was 17 points shy of silver and 31 points away from gold.
So it wasn't close.
Just about mustering a smile, more of a grin than a smile really from He Chong.
There's bronze for China.
And there's silver for China.
Here's somebody who missed out on a medal last year at the World Championships in fourth place.
He's gone too better this time.
Chen Kai of China.
Well, he's punching the air.
I think he's a bit more happy with that than He Chong.
Maybe he thought he was going to be a silver medalist anyway.
Didn't expect it to be a Russian who beat him to the first place.
Yeah, much bigger smile from the top ranked Chinese this time.
I think there might be a bit of a roar in this building when the gold medalist is announced.
A lot of people have stayed behind for the medal ceremony to acclaim, well, not totally unexpected gold medalist.
He was the silver medalist at the World Championships in Shanghai last year, but he has gone one better with 555.90 points.
Astonishing and remarkable.
Ilya Zakharov of Russia, 21 years of age, is the Olympic men's three meter springboard champion.
A big gold medal goes around his neck.
Delighted to take the acclaim of the crowd.
And he will be a powerhouse and a force to be reckoned with as long as the body holds together for the next few years.
He will be pushing the Chinese as he pushed them out the way today.
Ilya Zakharov breaks the stranglehold of the Chinese in diving events at London 2012.
And we will hear for the first time the Russian national anthem.
Please be upstanding for the national anthem of the Russian Federation.
you
Remember that face?
Remember the name.
Ilya Zakharov, the man who ended Chinese domination in the men's three meter springboard final with astonishing 104.50 on his final dive.
And an overall total of 555.90.
We think it was close.
14 points, virtually separating first and second.
So he did it his way.
He did it the hard way.
And he did it with that spectacular final dive.
It will have him immortalized in Russian diving history.
Last word for you, Leon.
Well, I don't know whether I've got any words to add to that.
Where can we go from here?
You know, we've got the women's platform and the men's platform still to go.
Same process, prelims in the evening, semifinals the next morning and then the final in the evening.
check the timings, check where you're going to be, because if the diving continues at this kind of standard, which I'm pretty confident it will, wow.
I'm going to run out of words to describe them.
Yep, we've gone from the three, we'll go to the ten for the women's and the men's at the weekend.
We are looking forward to that so much.
I hope that the ever-growing band
of diving aficionados and watchers will be with us for the women's and of course the men's to round off the program at the weekend.
Thank you for being with us here at the Aquatic Centre at the heart of London's Olympic Park.
It's been a tremendous night, particularly tremendous night for Russia and Russian diving.
What will happen in the women's 10 meter?
You'll find out with us in about 24 hours or less from now from Leon Taylor and myself, Bob Ballard.
Thank you for joining us.
Enjoy the rest of your day.
Yeah.
Ladies and gentlemen, that's the end of the impression that we have had today.
On behalf of the international living community, I'd like to welcome you to this fantastic occasion, and please stand for some inspiration.
We hope you enjoy your evening.
Thank you for being a part of this event.
Have a great journey, and we hope that you will continue to see the attractions as well.
Ready, now, go!